A Guide to the U.S. Forest Service. George Washington National Forest Dry River District Collection 1917-1994
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
U.S. Forest Service. George Washington National Forest Dry River District Collection 1917-1994
Special Collections, James Madison University
3014
This collection consists of one Hollinger box and twelve maps.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated Feb. 1998 by District Ranger Stephen Parsons.
Biographical/Historical Information
Fighting the forest arson prevalent during the first half of the twentieth century was at that time one of the U.S. Forest Service's foremost goals.
Scope and Content
Most file materials concern the Dry River District, which currently incorporates 227,000 acres on both sides of Shenandoah Mountain from state route 259 in the north to Lookout Mountain and state route 728 in the south, although locations in some other districts are mentioned. Most materials concern the fire-fighting activities undertaken by employees of Shenandoah National Forest, the predecessor of the George Washington National Forest. There are also some items relevant to recreational and historical topics.
Arrangement
Box 1, Oversize Box containing maps
Contents List
- Box 1
  - Recreation 1917-1934 (Folder 1)
    Includes a 1917 prospectus on Stribling Springs as a recreation site, with photos; and several pamphlets on recreation in national forests.
  - Camp Todd 1932-1968 (Folder 2)
    Several memos and photo detailing history of Camp Todd in the North River watershed, first settled in 1800 and used by the Forest Service in the 1920s and 30s for fire warden meetings, as a base for forest improvement operations, and as a summer vacation camp for VIPs, including Congressmen from Washington, D.C.
  - Fire Reports 1917-1919 (Folder 3)
    Forms with number of acres, cause of fire, cost of suppression, etc., for Spring Creek, Briery Branch, Edinburg, Armstrong, Deerfield, and several other locations.
  - High Knob Fire Tower 1946-1994 (Folder 4)
    Photo of the natural stone structure built on the Rockingham-Pendleton County line by Civilian Conservation Corp men 1939-40; memos concerning its construction and later renovation; and a 1994 list that includes the tower on the National Historic Lookout Register.
  - Fire warden system 1922-1957 (Folder 5)
    Correspondence, newsletters, and other documents detailing the inauguration of the system for selecting and training fire wardens in Shenandoah National Forest. Includes conference reports, fire fighting regulations, tracts for and against the long established custom of burning the woods, 1926 letters from the forest supervisor offering fire protection to landowners adjacent to the national forest, Pocket Guide for Fire Suppression (1961), and a small amount of statistical information.
  - Fire tower specifications 1917-1990 (Folder 6)
    General national forest specification; includes mention of High Knob tower. See also Oversize Box, below.
  - Civilian Conservation Corps photos (Folder 7)
    Copies of photographs taken in the 1930s of CCC men at work in several locations, including Camp Roosevelt. Not all pictures are identified.
- Oversize Box 1938
  One folder containing the 1938 Forest Service publication, Standard Lookout Structure Plans.
- Maps
  - Map no. 1 1917
    Massanutten National Forest
  - Map no. 2 1917
    Shenandoah National Forest.
  - Map no. 3 1920
    Shenandoah National Forest, oversize, with acquisitions boundaries.
  - Map no. 4 1925
    Massanutten Division, Shenandoah National Forest.
  - Map no. 5 1927
    Shenandoah National Forest, with text for general public.
  - Map no. 6 1927
    Shenandoah National Forest, with typed and penned text updates appended.
  - Map no. 7 1927
    Shenandoah National Forest, large.
  - Map no. 8 1927
    Shenandoah National Forest, with fire and ranger district boundaries drawn in and table of acreages.
  - Map no. 9 1927, 1932
    Shenandoah National Forest, with approved and recommended change in boundaries drawn in.
  - Map no. 10 1932
    George Washington National Forest, with text for general public.
  - Map no. 11 ca. 1930s
    George Washington National Forest, southern portion.
  - Map no. 12 1971
    George Washington National Forest Charcoal-Iron Furnaces.